<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ruby, | Franklin Webber]]></title>
  <link href="https://burtlo.github.com/blog/categories/ruby-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://burtlo.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-31T00:33:19-07:00</updated>
  <id>https://burtlo.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Franklin Webber]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Universal Frameworks for iOS made easy!]]></title>
    <link href="https://burtlo.github.com/blog/2012/03/25/universal-frameworks-for-ios-made-easy/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-25T15:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://burtlo.github.com/blog/2012/03/25/universal-frameworks-for-ios-made-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On a recent iOS project we wanted to integrate the
<a href="https://github.com/facebook/facebook-ios-sdk">Facebook iOS SDK</a>. The
integration went smoothy. We copied in the compiled library and the required
headers and were able to focus on the login, authentication flow.</p>

<h2>Problem</h2>

<p>However, we later ran into trouble with the library working on the device but
not in the simulator. We would fix it for the tests and the simulator but find
out we had broken it again for the device. This back and forth continued until we had found out about Universal Frameworks.</p>

<h2>Narrative</h2>

<p>We needed to compile the library in a format that would work on both on the
iPhone and the simulator. Google lead us to this <a href="http://db-in.com/blog/2011/07/universal-framework-iphone-ios-2-0/">invaluable post</a>
that outlined the arduous path of creating a universal framework. A journey
indeed filled with peril as there are so many opportunities along the way to
take a misstep and lose your way.</p>

<p>To the author's credit, he does a good job of outlining the necessary steps to
succeed. It is the shear overwhelming number of Xcode's <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/mac/#documentation/DeveloperTools/Reference/XcodeBuildSettingRef/1-Build_Setting_Reference/build_setting_ref.html">build settings</a>
that can get in the way with crossing the finish line.</p>

<p>As the project continued we came again to a similar crossroads as we needed to
include Twitter authentication. We chose to use the
<a href="https://github.com/thekarladam/MPOAuth">MPOAuth</a>
library but again found the need to generate a universal framework to save us
from the same particular annoyance (and others) that arose when it came time to
integrate the library. We followed through the same treacherous steps.</p>

<p>Having to do this twice has taught me that I do not want to do it again. There
is simply too many steps to get right. It was something that needed to be easier
and involve a lot less mouse-driven-development.</p>

<h2>Solution</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/rayh/xcoder">Xcoder</a> had the majority of the functionality to get started. However, it did
not have the ability to create some core components like: Aggregate Targets,
Copy Headers Build Phases, Run Script Build Phases.  At least it did not until
this <a href="https://github.com/rayh/xcoder/pull/24">weekend</a>.</p>

<p>I have created a <a href="https://gist.github.com/2201621">gist</a> that will generate a
universal framework with sources and header files. This should successfully
boil the the multiple page <a href="http://db-in.com/blog/2011/07/universal-framework-iphone-ios-2-0/">instructions</a> into roughly 100 lines of ruby code.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most valuable part is the ability to set the multitude of required
build settings, previously requiring deft configuration hunter skills, simply
with the following:</p>

<p><code>ruby
target.create_configurations :release do |config|
  config.always_search_user_paths = false
  config.architectures = [ "$(ARCHS_STANDARD_32_BIT)", 'armv6' ]
  config.copy_phase_strip = true
  config.dead_code_stripping = false
  config.debug_information_format = "dwarf-with-dsym"
  config.c_language_standard = 'gnu99'
  config.enable_objc_exceptions = true
  config.generate_debugging_symbols = false
  config.precompile_prefix_headers = false
  config.gcc_version = 'com.apple.compilers.llvm.clang.1_0'
  config.warn_64_to_32_bit_conversion = true
  config.warn_about_missing_prototypes = true
  config.install_path = "$(LOCAL_LIBRARY_DIR)/Bundles"
  config.link_with_standard_libraries = false
  config.mach_o_type = 'mh_object'
  config.macosx_deployment_target = '10.7'
  config.product_name = '$(TARGET_NAME)'
  config.sdkroot = 'iphoneos'
  config.valid_architectures = '$(ARCHS_STANDARD_32_BIT)'
  config.wrapper_extension = 'framework'
  config.info_plist_location = ""
  config.prefix_header = ""
  config.save!
end
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building iOS Apps in the Shell]]></title>
    <link href="https://burtlo.github.com/blog/2012/02/29/building-ios-app-in-the-shell/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-29T11:53:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://burtlo.github.com/blog/2012/02/29/building-ios-app-in-the-shell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The current state of iOS command-line tools for iOS is abysmal especially if you
are familiar and comfortable with a particular feedback loop for building,
testing, and deploying. It is code savagery! Plain and simple!</p>

<h2>Problem</h2>

<p>I wanted the ability to easily build Xcode targets from bash.</p>

<h2>Narrative</h2>

<p>As an iOS developer, if you use any testing library requiring an additional,
independent target you find yourself within Xcode re-selecting targets and
platforms during development to validate functionality. Xcode's programming is
predominately Mouse-Driven Development (MDD) and great for initial discovery but
that begins to break down as you start to identify multi-target operations you
want to perform quickly. This operation of switching targets/platforms is a
small cost if you write a lot of test or application code up front. This fails
when you want to test drive your development as this small operational cost adds
up as you begin to refine your feedback loop.</p>

<p>A project Substantial inherited came with a rudimentary <code>Rakefile</code> with a number
of tasks and helper methods defined to assist with building and testing an iOS
application from the command-line. It was awesome! As long as I did not block
the IOS simulator I could write code and tests and get more immediate feedback.</p>

<p>Sadly, it was largely wrong: composed of a number of variables and hard-coded
values that were based on assumptions of how the project was built. We hit our
first major problem upgrading all the developers from Xcode 3.x to Xcode 4.x.
All of our command-line tools and files broke and that quick feedback loop we
became accustomed to broke down. Because of it our team and others delivered
functionality that broke several tests that we later, out of context, struggled
to resolve.</p>

<p>With the start of our next project I immediately ported over the
<a href="https://gist.github.com/1953158">Rakefile</a> and took the opportunity to clean it
up. In a small amount of time I created some code that I was reasonably happy
with but again worried about having to drag a gist of code from project to
project. I thought about future me and I wanted to ensure I did not have to
remember any of this every again unless I absolutely needed.</p>

<h2>Solution</h2>

<p>It was then I went on the search for software to save me. It was then that I
stumbled upon <a href="http://rayh.com.au/">Rayh</a>'s
<a href="https://github.com/rayh/xcoder">xcoder</a>. I was able to throw away 200+ lines of
Rakefile to more elegantly write the following:</p>

<p>``` ruby Rakefile
require 'xcoder'</p>

<p>task :default => :specs</p>

<p>task :specs do
  Xcode.project('TestProject').target('Specs').config('Debug').builder.build
end
```</p>

<p>Gorgeous! And more importantly exceedingly more portable when I want to get
started on the right foot. To make this ever more portable I recently added
default rake tasks to the <a href="https://github.com/rayh/xcoder">xcoder</a> gem that adds
all your Xcode projects in your default directory available through rake.</p>

<p><code>ruby Rakefile
require 'xcoder/rake_task'
Xcode::RakeTask.new
</code></p>

<p>Which will generate several common tasks for each of your projects > targets >
configurations</p>

<p><code>bash rake output
rake xcode:test_project:specs:debug:build                   # Build TestProject Specs Debug
rake xcode:test_project:specs:debug:clean                   # Clean TestProject Specs Debug
rake xcode:test_project:specs:debug:package                 # Package TestProject Specs Debug
rake xcode:test_project:specs:debug:test                    # Test TestProject Specs Debug
rake xcode:test_project:specs:release:build                 # Build TestProject Specs Release
rake xcode:test_project:specs:release:clean                 # Clean TestProject Specs Release
rake xcode:test_project:specs:release:package               # Package TestProject Specs Release
rake xcode:test_project:specs:release:test                  # Test TestProject Specs Release
</code></p>

<p>Now the <code>Rakefile</code> looks something like:</p>

<p>``` ruby Rakefile
require 'xcoder/rake_task'
Xcode::RakeTask.new</p>

<p>task :default => "xcode:text_project:specs:debug:build"
```</p>

<p>The benefit is that <a href="(https://github.com/rayh/xcoder">Xcoder</a> is leveraging the
project file to generate the correct <code>xcodebuild</code> operation allowing your build
to remain in lock-step with the Xcode environment as you build and test your
product in a headless environment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
